Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series, Videorecordings V0058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings
  - The Bagel: A Systolic Concurrent Prolog Machine, by Prof. Ehud Shapiro., 1984-01-04; V0058.030; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)
    It is argued that explicit mapping of processes to processors is essential to effectively program a general-purpose parallel computer, and, as a consequence, that the kernel language of such a computer should include a process-to-processor mapping notation. The Bagel is a parallel architecture that combines concepts of dataflow, graphreduction, and systolic arrays with Turtle programs as a mapping notation. Concurrent Prolog, combined with Turtle programs, can easily implement systolic systems on the Bagel. Several systolic process structures are explored via programming examples, including linear pipes (sieve of Erasthotenes, merge sort, natural-language interface to a database), rectangular arrays (rectangular matrix multiplication, (band-matrix multiplication, dynamic programming, array relaxation), static and dynamic H-trees (divide-and-conquer, distributed database), and chaotic structures (a herd of Turtles). All programs have been debugged using the Turtle graphics Bagel simulator which is implemented in Prolog.
  - A Perspective on Automatic Programming, by Dr. David R. Barstow., 1984-02-07; V0058.031; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)
    Most work in automatic programming has focused primarily on the roles of deduction and programming knowledge. However, the role played by knowledge of the task domain seems to be at least as important, both for the usability of an automatic programming system and for the feasibility of building one that works on non-trivial problems. This perspective has evolved during the course of a variety of studies over the last several years, including detailed examination of existing software for a particular domain (quantitative interpretation of oil well logs) and the implementation of an experimental automatic programming system for that domain. The importance of domain knowledge has two important implications: a primary goal of automatic programming research should be to characterize the programming process for specific domains; and a crucial issue to be addressed in these characterizations is the interaction of domain and programming knowledge during program synthesis.
  - Reduced Instruction and Fast Operand Access for General-Purpose Microprocessors, by Prof. Manolis Katevenis., 1984-02-15; V0058.032; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 6)
    Even in VLSI, the transistors available on the limited chip area constitute a scarce resource when used for the implementation of a complete processor or computer, and thus, they have to be used effectively. General-purpose computations consist mostly of simple operations performed on frequently accessed operands, many of which are the few local scalar variables of procedures. The recent trend in general- purpose von Neumann computer architecture towards instruction sets of increasing complexity leads to inefficient use of the scarce on-chip resources. The alternative, Reduced Instruction Set Computers (RISC), make more effective use of on-chip transistors by using them in other functional units that do support frequent operations. The RISC II processor design and implementation has investigated the architectural implications of these observations. RISC II features simple instructions (like MIPS), and a large multi-window register file whose overlapping windows are used for holding the arguments and local scalar variables of the most recently activated procedures. The RISC II single-chip processor looks different from other popular commercial processors: it has fewer total transistors; it spends only 10% of the chip area for control, rather than 112 to 2/3; it has 138 32-bit registers; and it required about five times less design and lay-out effort to get chips that work correctly and at speed on first silicon. RISC II can execute integer, high-level language programs significantly faster than other processors made in similar technologies.
  - Algorithm Animation, by Prof. Robert Sedgewick, 1984-02-29; V0058.033; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 6)
    The central thesis of this talk is that it is possible to expose fundamental characteristics of computer programs through the use of dynamic (real time) graphic displays, and that such algorithm animation has the potential to be useful in several contexts. Recent research in support of this thesis is described, including the development of a conceptual framework for the process of animation, the implementation of a software environment on high-performance graphics-based workstations supporting this activity, and the use of the system as a principal medium of communication in teaching and research. Animated numerical, sorting, searching, string processing, geometric, and graph algorithms are described and illustrated.
  - Recent Progress on the Factoring Problem, by Prof. H.C. Williams., 1984-03-06; V0058.034; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 6)
    Given an integer N which is not prime, the problem of finding a,b> 1 such that N=ab is called the Factoring Problem. This problem has been studied for many centuries but the most significant progress on it has occurred only recently. New research has been stimulated by the invention of an elegant two key Cryptosystem (called RSA) which depends for its security on the presumed difficulty of the factoring problem. In this talk several methods of factoring are briefly discussed. These include some exciting new developments such as the recent implementation of the Quadratic Sieve, the development of special purpose hardware, and the proposed use of the Massively P~allel Processor. Some indication of the future progress on this problem is also given.
  - Designing Programs for Foreign Environments, by Steven H. Rempell., 1984-05-16; V0058.035; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 6)
    In order to survive in a highly competitive environment, software designers are finding it more and more imperative to take into account international requirements. This talk details many of the stumbling blocks to designing software that is translatable as well as flexible to local customs. Especially challenging are the foreign character sets. There are eleven different alphabets in Western Europe alone, each with its own keyboard arrangement, and 6000 characters of Japanese kanji. Conventions of name order, monetary systems, ad meanings of punctuation marks and symbols are a few of the other differences found between countries.
  - The Design of a Capability-Based Distributed Operating System, by Prof. Andrew S. Tanenbaum., 1984-05-22; V0058.036; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 6)
    The Computer Systems Group at the Vrije Universiteit is currently engaged in constructing a highly modular distributed operating system designed to run on a collection of 680oos, 8086s, and similar machines connected by a 10 Mbps tokenpassing ring. The operating system, Amoeba, has a very small kernel that supports multiprogramming and message passing. The rest of the operating system, including the file system, (most of the) memory management, process management, resource management, and so on, runs outside the operating system as user processes. The system is based on the client-server model, using a form of cryptographically protected capabilities to implement an object-oriented system. The talk discusses the overall design of the system and its distributed environment, how capabilities are managed in a protected way by untrusted user processes, the structure of a multiserver file system supporting multiple versions of files using optimistic concurrency control, and various other conceptual and implementation issues.
  - Making Smalltalk SOAR: Smalltalk on a RISC, by Prof. David A. Patterson., 1984-05-23; V0058.037; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 6)
    The SOAR project is a multi-month project to build a simple, Von Neumann computer that is designed to execute the Smalltalk-80 system faster than traditional computers. The Smalltalk-80 system is a highly productive programming environment, but poses tough challenges for implementors: dynamic data typing, a high level instruction set, frequent and expensive procedure calls, and object-oriented storage management. SOAR compiles programs to a low-level, efficient instruction set. Parallel tag checks permit high performance for the simple common cases and cause traps to software routines for the complex cases. Parallel register initialization and multiple on-chip register windows speed procedure calls. Sophisticated software techniques relieve the hardware of the burden of managing objects. Initial evaluations of the effectiveness of the SOAR architecture were arrived at by compiling and simulating benchmarks, and a 35,200-transistor NMOS chip is being fabricated. The early results suggest that a Reduced Instruction Set Computer can provide high performance in an exploratory programming environment.
  - The Search for Randomness, by Prof. Persi Diaconis., 1984-05-29; V0058.038; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 7)
    Computers simulate randomness by using simple recursive procedures such as congruential random number generators. Popular generators are surveyed along with recent work by George Marsaglia which proposes some new, simple tests which most good generators fail. These tests are sufficiently close to real world uses to give cause for alarm.
  - The Human Factor: Designing Computer Systems for People, by Dr. Dick Rubinstein., 1984-06-05; V0058.039; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 7)
    What principles of human factors--and what just plain good ideas--may be applied to the design of quality user interfaces? Dr. Rubinstein advances a number of principles and ideas that can make computer systems better for all users, including examples from the V AXstation user interface.
  - Designing High Performance MOS Circuits, by Mark Horowitz., 1984-10-03; V0058.040; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 7)
    To create a successful chip, it must not only function, but it must achieve a certain performance goal. This talk will describe some techniques used in industry to produce high performance MOS circuits, and will focus on CMOS design. The first part of the talk will review the basic issues in circuit design and point out the tradeoffs a circuit designer must make. The second part will focus on some general approaches to achieve high performance. This section will include precharge logic, domino logic, sense amplifiers, buffer sizing and others. Parts of the MIP-X processor will be used as example circuits.
  - Performance of Remote File Access and Processor Load Sharing In Locally Distributed Systems, by Prof. Edward D. Lazowska., 1984-10-09; V0058.04l; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 7)
    This talk describes two recent studies of design alternatives for locally distributed systems. The first study, conducted with John Zahorjan of the Univ. of Washington and David Cheriton and Willy Zwaenepoel of Stanford, considers the performance of single-user workstations that access files remotely from a shared file server. Our approach is to use the results of measurement experiments to parameterize queueing network performance models, which then are used to assess performance under load and to evaluate design alternatives. The second study, conducted jointly with Derek Eager of the Univ. of Toronto and John Zahorjan, addresses two fundamental questions about load sharing in homogeneous distributed systems: Whether the potential performance improvements can be realized in light of the overhead required, and whether system-wide state information is needed in making decisions about where to relocate work moved from a an overload node. Our approach is to use analytic models of artificial load sharing policies that optimistically and pessimistically bound the performance of realistic schemes. Our major conclusions are: load sharing results in improvements over a wide range of system loads, and so is a viable technique; very little is gained by maintaining extensive state information.
  - Computation and Communication in R*: A Distributed Database Manager, by Bruce G. Lindsay., 1984-10-30; V0058.042; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 7)
    This talk presents and discusses the computation and communication model used by R *, a prototype distributed database management system. An R * computation consists of a tree of processes connected by virtual circuit communication paths. The process management and communication protocols used by R * enable the system to provide reliable, distributed transactions while maintaining adequate levels of performance. Of particular interest is the use of processes in R * to retain user context from one transaction to another, in order to improve the system performance and recovery characteristics.
  - A Mixed VoicelData Network, by John Wakerly., 1984-10-31; V0058.043; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 7)
    The DAVID Information Manager carries voice, RS-232 data, and high-speed packets in a local area network using traditional telephone twisted-pair wiring in an office environment. This talk outlines the technical requirements for voice, data, and then describes the major hardware elements of the DA VID architecture. The talk includes brief descriptions of key topics in digital telephony, including pulse-code modulation, time-division multiplexing, circuit switching, and ping-pong transmission.
  - The Architecture of the Convex I -a 64-Bit Affordable Supercomputer, by Steve Wallach., 1984-11-07; V0058.044; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 8)
    This discussion will present the instruction set, internal register architecture, memory structure, and I/O structure of the Convex 1. There will also be a discussion on the optimizing and vectorizing FORTRAN compiler as well as the Convex version of 4.2 UNIX.
  - Implementing a Cache Consistency Protocol,by Prof. Randy Katz., 1984-11-20; V0058.045; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 8)
    We present an ownership-based multi-processor cache consistency protocol, designed for implementation by a single-chip VLSI cache controller. The protocol and its VLSI realization are described in some detail, to emphasize the important implementation issues in particular, the controller critical sections and the inter- and intra- cache interlocks needed to maintain cache consistency. The design has been carried out to layout in a p-well CMOS technology.
  - A Fast Compiler for Modula-2, by Prof. Niklaus Wirth. Edited copy., 1985-01-15; V0058.046; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 8)
    One-pass compilations has the advantage of being considerably faster than many-pass compilation, because it avoids the generations, storage, retrieval, and analysis of interpass codes On the other hand, it requires a relatively large main store. Since nowadays even "small" computers tend to have a considerable amount of memory, onepass compilers regain significance. We compare a new Modula-2 compiler with existing ones and describe its main structure. In particular, also some problems and their solution connected with separate compilation are discussed.
  - The Potential State of Computer and Information Technology in the Year 2000, by Prof. Stephen Lundstrom. Edited copy., 1985-01-23; V0058.047; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 8)
    At the request of NASA, the Aeronautics and Space Engineering Board (ASEB) of the National Academy of Science convened a workshop to assess the aeronautics technology possibilities by the year 2000. This workshop included panels to consider future aircraft system concepts, as well as the supporting disciplines of structures, aerodynamics, propulsion, human factors, materials, and guidance, navigation, and control. Since all of these disciplines are, or will be, highly dependent on advanced computer and information technology, a separate panel was convened to consider this area. The information presented in this talk is the result of the joint deliberations of the group of industry, university, and government experts from a wide range of areas who worked on the panel. The objective of these deliberations was to project what computer and information technology would be possible by the year 2000 if sufficient resources are made available. While the collective panel assembled had a very broad background, the conclusions reached were not unanimous, especially regarding the extent which various disciplines would be capable of progressing over this time frame. Undoubtedly, new research areas, unknown to the panelists, will emerge during this time frame. The projections given in the report are the honest options of most of the group assembled and while they cannot be supported with any quantitative analyses, they do represent an outlook to the future which is as realistic as possible. The topics considered by the panel, and reported in this talk, include: Microelectronics and Components, Processors (including scientific supercomputers and airborne distributed systems), Software, Artificial Intelligence and Expert Systems, ManMachine Interfaces, Systems Development and Implementation, and High Integrity Systems.
  - Knowledge Based Software Development in FSD, by Prof. Robert Balzer. Edited copy., 1985-02-25; V0058.048; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 8)
    Our group is pursuing the goal of an automation based software development paradigm. While this goal is still distant, we have embedded our current perceptions and capabilities in a prototype (FSD) of such a software development Although this prototype was built primarily as a testbed for our ideas, we decided to gain insight by using it, and have added some administrative services to expand it from a programming system to a computing environment currently being used by a few lSI researchers for all their computing activities. This "AI operating System" provides specification capabilities for Search, Coordination, Automation, Evolution, and Inter-User Interaction. Particularly important is evolution, as we recognize that useful systems can only arise, and remain viable, through continued evolution. Much of our research is focused on this issue and several examples will be used to characterize where we are today and where we are headed. Naturally, we have started to use these facilities to evolve our system.
  - The USC Expert Synthesis System, by Prof. Alice Parker. Edited copy., 1985-03-06; V0058.049; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 8)
    This talk presents a brief overview of the USC Expert Synthesis System, which is part of the ADAM (Advanced Design AutoMation) project. This system supports interactive specification of digital system design problems, and provides a framework for both interactive and automatic design synthesis of digital integrated circuits from specifications of the black box behavior Topics covered include the overall system structure, the representation of design information, and two specific synthesis problems -- the synthesis/verification of data path designs and the synthesis of clocking schemes. In addition, abstract system specification is covered briefly.
  - The Theory and Application of Non-First-Normal-Form Relations, by Prof. Henry Korth. Edited copy., 1985-03-12; V0058.050; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)
    In this talk, we present a formal model for the study of non- INF relational databases. A formal relational calculus is defined and this calculus is proved equivalent to an extension of the standard relational algebra. We define a new normal form for nonINF relations and define several new algebraic operators that preserve this normal form. In the ROSI (Relational Operating System Interface) project at the University of Texas, we are using our model of non-lNF relations to construct a relational user interface to an operating system environment. The ROSI query languages currently being designed include an extended version of SQL for non-lNF relations, and a graphical query language based on an extension to universal-relation languages. In this talk, we present a preliminary design of these languages.
  - The Status. Trends and Challenges in Information Storage Technology, by Prof. A.S. Hoagland. Edited Copy., 1985-03-13; V0058.051; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)
    Magnetic recording has played the predominant role in meeting the growing needs for data storage for over 30 years, and during this period storage density consistently has doubled about every two years. Yet we are just now witnessing an explosive growth in the application of this technology for the storage of information, and technological advances are beginning to accelerate. At the same time, optical storage is just beginning to be introduced in commercial storage devices at much higher densities than currently available. However, density itself may be of much less significance in the long term than functional features related to usage. The evolution of information of storage technologies and devices will be traced and their future prospects will be discussed. The potential competitive and complementary roles of magnetic and optical storage will be related to emerging applications. This talk is a quick overview of a subject which is to be covered in a much more extensive and comprehensive form in a series of videotapes being prepared by the Institute for Information Storage Technology at the University of Santa Clara that are to be made generally available to industry
  - On the Sequential Nature of Unification, by Prof. Cynthia Dwork., 1985-04-09; V0058.052; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)
    Unification of terms is a crucial step in resolution theorem proving, with applications to a variety of symbolic computation problems. It will be shown that the general problem is log-space complete for P, even if infinite substitutions are allowed. Thus a fast parallel algorithm for unification is unlikely. More positively, term matching, an important subcase of unification, will be shown to have a parallel algorithm requiring a number of processors polynomial in n, the size of the input, and running in time polylogarithmic in n. This talk assumes no familiarity with unification or its applications
  - Graphics for User Interfaces, by Prof. Vaughan Pratt., 1985-04-16; V0058.053; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)
    Responsive user interfaces need high performance high quality graphics support. I shall describe recent research at Sun addressing the graphics needs of text, splines, and windows.
  - The GEM Programming EnvironmentlUser Interface, by Timothy Oren. Edited master; Umatic dub." ", 1985-04-24; V0058.054; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)
    GEM (Graphics Environment Manager), a program created at Digital Research, Incorporated, brings the familiar menu/ icon! windowing environment of the Xerox star to the IBM PC, the Atari ST series, and other personal computers. Unlike other environments of this type, GEM provides a large degree of source code compatibility between different machines and machine configurations, allowing applications to be ported with relatively little effort.
  - Statistical Mechanics of Concurrency, by Prof. Yechiam Yemini., 1985-05-07; V0058.055; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)